Finding Aid for the Denna Frank Fleming Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Denna Frank Fleming Papers
2013
1893-1989
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0706
2.95 linear_feet
Scope and Content Note for the Addition
This Addition to the Denna Frank Fleming Papers came to Vanderbilt University Special Collections after the death of Mrs. Doris Fleming in 1989. It measures 4.26 linear feet and is contained in 7 full Hollinger boxes and one oversize box and covers the years 1893 - 1989. It completes the Denna Frank Fleming Papers which were given to Vanderbilt in February 1981, and which measure 7.55 cubic feet, 21 Hollinger boxes.
These papers include materials from several areas of his life and work - those of teacher, writer, political scientist, concerned citizen, husband, friend, and colleague.
Series List:
The Correspondence includes personal letters, letters with publishers, and testimonial letters both before and after his death.
Personal and Biographical materials includes a narrative of Fleming’s life written by his wife Doris S. Fleming; memorials by colleagues and friends, tributes at the memorial service with the order of service, and other items dating from his birth.
Academic Career papers include correspondence with Vanderbilt University administration, announcements of his lectures, conferences, and other professional activities, and papers by a former student J. Louis Adams.
The Writings series includes material on books, articles, addresses, scripts of radio broadcasts, reviews and an extensive collection of comments by others about Fleming’s publications and radio broadcasts.
Publications are comprised of a small number of publications by others.
The Subject Files contain collections of papers on the D.F. Fleming - Johns Committee Affair, 1961, his conflict with James Maddox, his collection of materials about Southeast Asia, the Vietnam War, and other topics of interest to Dr. Fleming over his long career as a professor and political scientist.
Photographs and Slides include images from his many travels and personal photographs of Dr. Fleming and his wife Doris.
The Memorabilia is contained in one oversize box of keepsake items belonging to Dr. Fleming and includes a Distinquished Service Award from the Nashville Chapter United Nations Association, May 17, 1977; a plaque with program from the Appreciation Dinner honoring Fleming at Belmont United Methodist Church, May 17, 1977; his Phi Beta Kappa key ( alpha of Tennessee,1940); his gold and enamel 50 year Masonic pin (square and compass), and his 1928 gold Phi Kappa Phi key (University of Illinois collegiate honor society for all disciplines). Other keepsake items include a small army issue New Testament, and a collection of first day issues for the United Nations Association, 1971.
Biographical Chronology for D.F. Fleming
1893 Born in Paris, Illinois to Albert and Eleanor McCormick Fleming, March 25
1905 - 1912 Eastern Illinois State College
1912 - 1914 Principal of High School, Hume, Illinois
1916 High School Teacher, Freeport, Illinois A.B., University of Illinois
1917 High School Teacher, Walla Walla, Washington
1918 Aircraft Machine Gun Instructor in France
1919 - 1921 Superintendent of Schools, Tonica, Illinois
1920 A.M., University of Illinois
1921 - 1922 Superintendent of Schools, Colfax, Illinois
1922 - 1923 Assistant Professor, Monmouth College, Monmouth, Illinois
1923 - 1924 Associate Professor, Monmouth College, Monmouth, Illinois
1924 - 1927 Professor & Head of Department, Monmouth College, Monmouth, Illinois
1926 - 1927 Summer Instructor, Iowa State Teachers College
1928 Ph.D., University of Illinois
1928 - 1930 Assistant Professor, Vanderbilt University
1929 Married Doris Sigrid Anundsen, June 29
1930 The Treaty Veto of the American Senate
1930 - 1938 Associate Professor, Vanderbilt University
1932 - 1933 Penfield Traveling Scholar. Attended Disarmament Convention in Geneva
1932 Published The United States and the League of Nations, 1918 - 1920
1934 - 1937 Columnist for Th e Tennessean
1935 Attended talks on the Ethiopian Crisis, Geneva
1938 Professor, Vanderbilt; in London during the Munich Crisis; Published The United States and World Organization, 1920 -1933
1938 - 1939 Penfield Traveling Scholar
1937 - 1947 Commentator on foreign affairs for WSM Radio Station, Nashville, Tennessee
1940 - 1951 Head of the Political Science Department, Vanderbilt University
1941 President of the Southern Political Science Association
1943 Vice-President of the American Political Science Association
1943 Can We Win the Peace
1944 While America Slept
1944 - 1946 Radio Commentator, Woodrow Wilson Foundation
1945 Published The United States and the World Court. Founded the Nashville chapter of the Association for the United Nations
1946 Member of Bernard Baruch's staff in the State Department during the atomic energy negotiations with the U.S.S.R.
1946, 1948 - 49 Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton University
1949 Honorary degree, Pe.D., Eastern Illinois University
1950 - 1955 Board of Directors, Woodrow Wilson Foundation
1951 Research Professor, Vanderbilt University
1952 - 1960 Columnist for Classmate (Methodist Publication)
1954 - 1957 Executive Council, The American Association of University Professors
1954 Fulbright Lecturer, Cambridge University
1956 Delegate to the Fifth National Conference of the U.S. National Convention for UNESCO for the AAUP
1956 - 1962 Columnist for the British Weekly
1957 Phi Beta Kappa Associates
1959 - 1960 Fulbright Lecturer, School of International Studies, New Delhi, India
1961 Retired from Vanderbilt University, published The Cold War and Its Origins, Vol. I, 1917 -1950, Vol. II, 1950 - 1960
1964 Visiting Lecturer, University of Arizona, Tucson
1965 Visiting Lecturer, California State College at Los Angeles
1966 Visiting Professor, University of Arizona, Tucson
1968 Published The Origins and Legacies of World War I
1969 Visiting Professor, Simon Fraser University, Vancouver, British Columbia
1969 America’s Role in Asia
1970 Taught at Middle Tennessee State University
1972 Published Issues of Survival
1975 Distinquished Alumni Award, Eastern Illinois University
1980 Died September 03, age 87, in Nashville
- Correspondence - Outgoing
  - September 30, 1940 - December 1, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - January 18, 1971 - November 15, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1932; 1980 - 1981 from Doris S. Fleming (on the death of DFF) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Incoming
  - Ballard, Hoyt B (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Barber, Willard
    - Brands, Maarten C
    - Burnie, Nadreen
    - Capouya, Emile
    - Colyer, Dorothy
    - Compton, John
    - Crabb Durham, Anna
  - Farnen, Russell, Jr (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fleming, Doris
  - Gundy, H. Pearson (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Haefele, Marc
    - Holloway, James Y
    - Holmes
    - Jamison, Bill
    - Johnson, Victor
    - Jones, Neal O
    - Kendall, L. M
    - Kominsky, Morris
    - MacInnes, E.D
  - Manfred, Ernest F (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Manton, Thomas B
    - Martin, Dan M
    - Miller, J. W
    - Miller, W. T
    - Monypenny, Phillip
    - Moore, Lewis E., Jr
    - The Nation
    - Ransom, Steve (for Shepardson)
    - Read, Harry
    - Reed, Forrest F
    - Ruggie, John Gerard
  - Schick, Franz B (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Scott, David
    - Sills, Joe Byrns
    - Smith, Jessica
    - Smith, Robert H
    - Swint, Henry Lee
    - United Nations Association
    - Ward, James E
    - Weaver, E.E
  - Fleming Family letters (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Following the Death of D.F. Fleming, September 3, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - From Friends at the Death of D.F. Fleming (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - From Chantal and Ole ( last name unknown) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Not identified (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - With George Allen and Unwin Ltd., Publishers, 1967 - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Doris Fleming with Louise Vidaud de Flaud, October 1983 - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Personal and Biographical
  - Affidavit concerning the birth of Denna Frank Fleming, March 25, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Honorable discharge from the United States Army, February 12, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - University of Illinois - final examination of Denna F. Fleming for the Ph.D., May 31, 1928 with summary of his thesis: The Ratification of Treaties (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Wedding announcement, June 29, 1929; newspaper announcement “D. F. Fleming Married” (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Article about Fleming, “Intellectual Approach to Circulation Growth Proves Valid in Nashville, August 10, 1935; Notebook, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Honorary degree Eastern Illinois State College, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters of appreciation, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes for an interview, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Excerpt from an article by Lamar Alexander, editor of the Vanderbilt Hustler, November 3, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Article on D.F. Fleming “Academic Freedom and Tenure: The University of South Florida” reprinted from AAUP Bulletin, the Spring Issue, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Article in The Eastern Alumnus “ A Distinquished Graduate Writes”, September 1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notice of lecture”Can the Extinction of Man Be Averted?”, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Newspaper article “D.F. Fleming Vanderbilt’s First Radical” March 18, 1970 in Vanderbilt Hustler (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - A Year End Letter from the D.F. Flemings - 1971; list of books on China, Japan, and Germany (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Distinquished Alumni Award Eastern Illinois University, May 11, 1975, newsletter and correspondence (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Program of UNA/USA Nashville Chapter dinner honoring D.F. Fleming, May 17, 1977 with accompanying testimonial letters (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Obituary from The Tennessean, September 4, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Tribute to Dr. D.F. Fleming at his memorial service September 3, 1980 by Fred Cloud; Harry Howe Ransom; and a former student (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Order of service, memorial service for D.F. Fleming, September 10, 1980 at Belmont United Methodist Church, Nashville, Tennessee (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Testimonials by colleagues and friends (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Testimonials from former students (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters of condolence on the death of D.F. Fleming (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Program - International Night Celebration dedicated to Dr. D. F. Fleming, October 21, 1980, United Nations Associaton - Nashville Chapter (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Information for Who’s Who in America, editorial revision sheet, 1980 Information for Contemporary Authors (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Presidential certificate of honor, 1981 (Jimmy Carter) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letter to Mrs. Fleming from Eastern Illinois University, March 10, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Narrative of D.F.F.’s life by Doris Fleming to Steven J. Bucklin, 1988 - 89 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Data concerning D.F. Fleming (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Post retirement activity (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Biographical information (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Comments on lectures and radio broadcasts (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Personal and Biographical
  - Material for a piece on D.F. Fleming (1) Letters from Fleming to Synder, 1928 - 1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Material for a piece on D.F.Fleming (2) Biographical narrative (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Material for a piece on D.F. Fleming (3) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Material for a piece on D.F. Fleming (4) Memorials (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Material on Albert Fleming and D.F. Fleming (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Edmonds - Brock Family (Doris Anundsen Fleming) Research Materials” (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Edmonds - Brock Family Building an investment Portfolio by the Valuator (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Marriage certificate of Emily A. Brock and Alfred Anundsen, January 23, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Items and materials relating to Doris A. Fleming (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lists of civic, commerce, and trade organizations (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Legal documents - contracts with publishers (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Academic Career
  - New York Times references to Permanent Court of International Justice Readers Guide references to Permanent Court of International Justice Holograph notes New York Times article, January 5, 1934 “World Court Vote Held Inopportune” (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Southeastern International Relations Clubs, Fifteenth Conference at Vanderbilt University, March 4 - 5, 1938 Norman Wait Harris Memorial Foundation, Sixteenth Institute, The Foundations Of a More Stable World Order, University of Chicago, June 23 to July 3, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Vanderbilt University administration, 1938 - 1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Vanderbilt University administration concerning publications and teaching duties and other, 1954; 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence concerning the end of his career at Vanderbilt and offer of another Position, 1961 - 62 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - “Twenty-five Assumptions Underlying the American End of the Cold War as They Developed from 1945 to 1952” (posed by D.F. Fleming) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Statements about Fleming’s work, 1967; 1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Letters from students, 1945, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - “What does Russia Want?” an estimate “Is Communism Just as Bad as Fascism?” A memorandum (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Announcement of lectures by Fleming at Vanderbilt and other (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Article - reprint - “Academic Freedom and Tenure: the University of South Florida” AAUP Bulletin, Spring issue, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Student papers – Adams, J. Louis - “Valuation of Property Paid for Stock” for Corporation Finance - Mr. Sowards - Vanderbilt University Law School, August 30, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis “ Valuation of Property Paid for Stock” for Corporation Finance - Mr. Sowards - Vanderbilt University Law School, August 30, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis “Valuation of Property Paid for Stock: A Reappraisal” in Miami Law Quarterly, Vol.III, no. 1, December 1948 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis “American Neutrality During the Wars of the French Revolution and the Napoleonic Era” for Political Science 405a American Foreign Affairs (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis - Research Notes for Political Science 416, April 1946 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis - “Questions and Problems in Insurance” Dr. E. J. Eberling, Economics 426 Insurance, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Student Papers/Publications - Adams, J. Louis - Old Purdy:the History of the First County Seat of McNairy County, Tennessee, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Books removed from the Fleming Collection to Central Library Vanderbilt University (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Copies of “Declaration of Independence” and “A Bill of Rights - Constitution of the United States” (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Business and Public Administration: A New Program at Vanderbilt University (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Academic Career
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis - for courses at Cumberland University, Lebanon, TN, 1939 - 1941; Shenandoah College, Dayton, Virginia, 1941 - 1943 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis - Political Science, Government and Business, Constitutional Law, Insurance, Summer Term at Vanderbilt University, June 10 August 23, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Student Papers - Adams, J. Louis - Political Science, Summer Term, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Books - America’s Role in Asia
  - Correspondence with publishers, reviews, royalty statements (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Books - Can We Win the Peace?
  - Press comments and press releases (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Books - The Cold War and Its Origins, 1917 - 1960
  - Correspondence with publishers, January 23, 1967 - October 25, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with publishers, November 6, 1967 - January 30, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Review and correspondence concerning review by John L. Snell in American Historical Review, January 19, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Barraclough, Geoffrey in The Nation, December 2, 1961
    - Benson, Oliver in The Annals of the American Academy, July, 1962
    - Berding, Andrew in Washington, D.C. Star, November 26, 1961
    - Delzell, Charles F. in Nashville Banner, December 15, 1961
    - DuBoff, Richard B. in The Nation, March 6, 1967
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Fremont-Smith, Eliot in The New York Times, May 2, 1968
    - Goff, Martyn in The Times Literary Supplement, September 15, 1961
    - Graebner, Norman A. in Bulletin of the Atomic Scientist
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Halperin, S. William in Chicago Sunday Tribune, November 26, 1961
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Houghton, Neal D. in The Western Political Quarterly
    - McKitterick, T. E. M. in The Political Quarterly of London, Vol. 33, 1962
    - Roberts, Henry L. in The New York Times, December 24, 1961
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Schuman, Frederick L. in New World Review, February, 1962
    - Thursby, Vincent V. in The Journal of Politics, Vol. 24, October 1962
  - Comments from the Press (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Three letters received in late, July 1963 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Early Press Excerpts (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Comments on the First Printing (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Review Excerpts - Second Series (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Review Excerpts - Third Series (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Third Series - Excerpts from letters (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Third Series - Excerpts from letters (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Fourth Series - Excerpts from letters (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Sixth Series - Excerpts from letters (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Comments from reviews (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Excerpts from the British Press (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Excerpts from letters (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Excerpts from later letters (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Other reviews (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Recent comments (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Excerpts from reviews (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Comments, August, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Statement by Dr. Arnold Toynbee; statement by Philip Noel - Baker (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - An evaluation by James Avery Joyce in End of an Illusion (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Letter to Editor, Slavic Review, September 1963 concerning review by William Henry Chamberlin in, September 1962 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Books - Does Deterrence Deter?
  - A Study and Commentary in The Beyond Deterrence Series, Copyright 1962, American Friends Service Committee (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Books - The Origins and Legacies of World War I
  - Correspondence with publishers, November 8, 1967, August 26, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Letter in New York Times, February 23, 1969 from D.F. Flemig concerning a Review by Gordon Craig (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Comments compiled by publisher Doubleday; comments by Gunnar Myrdal and Arnold Toynbee (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Reviews by others: “Fifty Years Later and Still no Armistice” by Arnold J. Toynbee in Washington Post Book World, November 10, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Books - Stages in the Cold War - Essays, 1945 - 1965
  - Introduction by Robert M. Hutchins and accompanying letter, September 8, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Books - The Treaty Veto of the American Senate
  - Comments by the Press (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Books - The United States and the League of Nations, 1918 -1920
  - Correspondence with publishers Russell and Russell (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Comments (1932) (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Books - The United States and the World Court
  - Correspondence - Incoming (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Jones, Rupert, March 6, 1945
    - Schriftgiesser, Karl, January 29, 1945
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Anderson, Stanley in Cleveland Press, February 6, 1945
    - Kenkrick, Alexander in Philadelphia Inquirer, February 11, 1945
    - MacIver, R. M. in New York Times Book Review, March 4. 1945
    - Reynolds, Morgan in Nashville Banner, February 21, 1945
    - Schriftgiesser, Karl in Newsweek, February 12, 1945; Tennessean, Washington Post; Witherspoon, Frances in Herald Tribune; February 25, 1945; February 26, 1945
  - Comments of reviewers and press releases (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Books - The United States and the World Organization, 1920 -1933 (1938)
  - Comments by reviewers (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Review of 3 books by Fleming: The United States and the World Organization, The United States and the League of Nations; The Origins and Legacies of World War (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Farnen, Russell F., Jr. in Nashville Banner, December 27, 1968
    - Thursby, Vincent V. in The Journal of Politics, Vol. 31, 1969
  - Review by of six books by Fleming Parks, Norman L. in The Nation, February 3, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Radio Broadcasts - America and the World Crisis
  - Comments, 1940 - 1944 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Comments from 30 states on broadcasts by Fleming from Station WSM, Nashville, Tennessee (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Comments, May 16, 1040, December 23, 1945 (56 pages ) (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Selected comments, May 29, 1940, April 27, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Listener comments, June 1944, March 1945 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Comments by listeners, February 9, 1940, September 7, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 53)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Radio Broadcasts - “How Can We Make the Victory Stick?”
  - A Series of Thirteen Radio Broadcasts by Dr. Denna F. Fleming, March, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Script with accompanying materials - stations carrying the broadcasts and comments of radio station managers, October - December 1945 (Box 4, Folder 55)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Radio Broadcasts - “The Middle East Crisis”
  - Typescript (Box 4, Folder 56)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Radio Broadcasts - “Undercurrents and Current Events”
  - Typescript of a broadcast on WSM Radio Station, Sunday, June 11, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Writings by D. F. Fleming - Radio Broadcasts - While America Slept (1944)
  - Comments of reviewers and press releases (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Reviews (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Brock, H. I. in The New York Times Book Review, March 5, 1944
    - Edstrom, Ed in Louisville Courier Journal, March 5. 1944
    - Harris, Sydney Justin in Chicago Daily News, March 15, 1944
    - Reynolds, Morgan in Nashville Banner, February 23, 1944
      (Recordings of many of these broadcasts are in boxes 25 and 26 of the Radio Recording Collection housed at 21 North Archives Annex for Vanderbilt University. A listing of the items in these boxes is at the end of this finding aid.)
- Writings by D.F. Fleming - Articles and Reprints
  - “The Role of Fear and Hindsight in World Politics” in The Western Political Quarterly, Vol. III, no. 4, December 1950 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - “Collier’s Wins World War III” in The Nation, November 10, 1951; response to this “ article in The Nation, December 8, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - “What Follows the Arms Race?” in The Journal of Politics, May 1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - “How Can We Secure Dependable Allies?” reprinted from The Annals of American Academy of Political and Social Science, Philadelphia, September, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - “Are We Headed Toward Another World War?” from The Western Political Quarterly, Vol. V, no. 3, September, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - “Are You Afraid?” a page on the place of the church in World Affairs in Classmate, March 1, 1953, Vol. 60, no. 9 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - “Are We Moving Toward Fascism?” in The Journal of Politics, February 1954 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - In Classmate(The International Outlook, ( a Methodist publication):
    - “The Coming Crisis Over Indo-China”, January 1, 1956